Inventory of the American Association for Higher Education records
Hoover Institution Archives
American Association for Higher Education records
1944-2006
2006C6
Hoover Institution Archives
166 manuscript boxes (69.2 linear feet)
The collection relates to higher education in the United States. It consists of minutes, conference and meeting materials, correspondence, memoranda, reports, studies, publications, membership records, and video recordings.
American Association for Higher Education
Access
Collection is open for research. Collection stored off site; a minimum of two days notice is required for use. Boxes may be requested through Stanford's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2006.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
American Council on Education records, Hoover Institution Archives
Academy for Educational Development records, Hoover Institution Archives
Council for Basic Education records, Hoover Institution Archives
Historical Note
The American Association for Higher Education (AAHE) originated as the department of higher education of the National Education Association (NEA) in 1870. After almost a century of working under NEA leadership (with a hiatus from 1924 to 1942 when the AAHE briefly disbanded), the association became an independent, non-profit agency in 1969. Members of the AAHE included faculty members, administrators, graduate students, and trustees regardless of their affiliation or discipline. According to its own publication, the association was "dedicated to the professional development of college and university educators, to the achievement of their education objectives, and to the improvement of conditions of service" (Smith, 1970). The association ended in 2005 following a vote by the Board of Directors.
Sources:
Miller, Margaret A. (September/October 2005). "AAHE's Legacy." Change, 37(5), pp. 8-20. Retrieved August 26, 2011 from WilsonWeb Education Full Text database.
Smith, G. K., & American Association for Higher Education. (1970). Twenty-five years, 1945-1970. San Francisco: Jossey-Bass.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection relates to higher education in the United States. It consists of minutes, conference and meeting materials, correspondence, memoranda, reports, studies, publications, membership records, and video recordings.
The archives of the Association for Higher Education (AAHE) were created and maintained at the association's former headquarters in Washington D.C. The Presidential correspondence series includes mainly routine correspondence; some with the association's major grant funders, including the Pew Charitable Trust and Carnegie Corporation, regarding project developments. Records of the association's ongoing projects are in the Project file.
Some major projects represented in the records include the Forum on Faculty Roles and Rewards, New Pathways II-Academic Careers for a New Century: From Inquiry to Practice, and the Urban Universities Portfolio Project (a joint project with the Pew Charitable Trust). Published papers, journals, and other serials related to these projects appear in the Publications series.
Consisting mainly of reports, agendas, minutes, and correspondence from Board of Directors meetings, the Meeting materials series provides information on the association's annual budget, ongoing projects, elections process, and conference planning. Although the National Conference of Higher Education, the association's most successful and widely attended event, was often a topic of interest at board meetings, the published programs and pamphlets from the NCHE and other annual conferences appear in the Conference materials series.
Limited arrangement was performed by archives staff and original folder titles were used when provided. Boxes containing related materials were grouped together. Materials may not always be in chronological or alphabetical order.
Incremental materials received in 2013 include additional correspondence of AAHE's last president, Clara Lovett, as well as documentation on the organization's dissolution in 2005.
Education--United States.; Universities and colleges--United States.
- General records, 1953-1982; 1-3 (Box 1-3)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes correspondence and legal documents relating to the founding of AAHE and it's separation from the National Education Association, as well as general background materials
  - Bibliographies on higher education, 1963-1972 (Folder 1)
  - Election of officers, 1969-1974 (Folder 1)
  - Presidential correspondence, 1965-1969 (Folder 1)
  - Organizational mission and function, 1959-1971 (Folder 1)
  - Election of officers, 1974-1982 (Folder 2)
  - National Conference statistics, 1979-1981 (Folder 3)
  - Resolutions of the Association for Higher Education, 1948-1968 (Folder 3)
  - Maxwell, Grace Rushing. An Historical Survey and Analysis of the Annual Conferences on Higher Education of the Association for Higher Education, 1964 (Folder 3)
  - So they say about higher education. [Washington]: Association for Higher Education. Vols. 1-10, 1953-1962 (Folder 3)
- Presidential correspondence, 1972-2005; 4-16 (Box 4-16)
  Includes routine correspondence and some memoranda of AAHE presidents
  - Russell Edgerton (Folder 4-9)
    - 1994 (Folder 4)
    - 1993-1994 (Folder 5)
    - 1993 (Folder 6)
    - 1992-1993 (Folder 7)
    - 1992, 1997 (Folder 8)
      Includes some correspondence of others
    - 1996 (Folder 9)
  - Margaret A. Miller, 1998-2000 (Folder 10)
  - Margaret A. Miller, 1999 (Folder 11-12)
  - Yolanda Moses, 2001-2003 (Folder 12)
  - Yolanda Moses, 2002 July-December (Folder 13)
    Includes some conference materials
  - Yolanda Moses, 2000-2001 (Folder 14)
  - Clara Lovett, 2003-2005 January (Folder 14)
  - Correspondence and project proposals, 1972-1976, 1990-1991 (Folder 15)
  - Anne Yates Society, 1981-1987 (Folder 15)
  - Correspondence and project proposals, 1990-1991 (Folder 16)
- Meeting materials, 1944-2005; 16-50 (Box 16-50)
  Includes agendas, minutes, brochures, correspondence, memoranda, and reports from Board of Directors and committee meetings
  - Board of Directors meeting memoranda and minutes, 1988-1992 (Folder 16)
  - Constituency Group Leaders meeting materials, 2000 (Folder 16)
  - New board member orientation manual, 2004 (Folder 17: 1)
  - Constituency Group Leaders meeting materials, 2001-2002 (Folder 17: 2-3)
  - Fall Board Retreat, 1997 October (Folder 17: 4)
  - Board of Directors meeting memoranda and minutes, 1995-1997 (Folder 17: 5-10)
  - Board of Directors and Executive Committee meeting minutes, 1946-1958 (Folder 18)
  - Board of Directors meeting materials, 1958-1961 (Folder 19)
  - Board of Directors meeting materials, 1962-1963 (Folder 20)
  - Board of Directors meeting materials, 1963-1965 (Folder 21)
  - Board of Directors meeting materials, 1967-1971 (Folder 22)
  - Board of Directors files, 1969-1985 (Folder 23)
  - Lists of committees, 1971-1972 (Folder 23)
  - Board of Directors meeting materials, 1971-1974 (Folder 24)
  - Board of Directors meeting materials, 1975-1977 (Folder 25)
  - Bozrd of Directors meeting materials, 1978-1980 (Folder 26)
  - Board of Directors meeting materials, 1981-1983 (Folder 27)
  - Board of Directors meeting materials, 1983-1984 (Folder 28)
  - Constitution and by-laws, 1974-1980 (Folder 29)
  - Board of Directors memoranda and reports, 1983-1986 (Folder 29)
  - Board of Directors meeting minutes, 1974 (Folder 29)
  - Board of Directors meeting materials, 1988-1989, 1994 (Folder 30)
  - Board of Directors meeting materials, 1989-1992 (Folder 31)
  - Board of Directors meeting materials, 1988-1996 (Folder 32)
  - Board of Directors meeting materials, 1990-1992 (Folder 33)
  - Board of Directors meeting materials, 1991-1996 (Folder 34)
  - Board of Directors meeting materials, 1992-1995 (Folder 35)
  - Board of Directors meeting materials, 1993-1996 (Folder 36)
  - Board of Directors meeting minutes, 1997 (Folder 37)
  - Voluntary leadership meeting and retreat materials, 1995-1996 (Folder 37)
  - "The AAHE Reader,", 1994 October (Folder 38)
  - Voluntary Leaders' retreat, 1998 September (Folder 38)
  - Leadership conference materials, 1997 September (Folder 38)
  - Board of Directors meeting materials, 1985-1986 (Folder 38)
  - Board of Directors meeting materials, 1998 October (Folder 39)
  - Board retreat, 1997 October (Folder 39)
  - Board of Directors meeting materials, 1998 May (Folder 40: 1)
  - Board of Directors meeting materials, 1999 (Folder 40: 2)
  - AAHE Board roster, 2003 (Folder 40: 3)
  - Board contacts, 2000-2001 (Folder 40: 4)
  - Board ballot information, 2004 (Folder 40: 5)
  - Service learning-volume marketing, 2001-2002 (Folder 40: 6)
  - Board of Directors meeting materials, 1999-2000 (Folder 41)
  - Board of Directors meeting memoranda and minutes, 2001-2003 (Folder 42)
  - Board of Directors meeting materials and presidential search committee files, 2002-2003 (Folder 43)
  - Board of Directors meeting materials, 2003-2004 (Folder 44)
  - Board of Directors meeting materials, 2005 (Folder 45)
    Includes votes to end AAHE
  - National Committee on General Education meeting materials, 1949-1958 (Folder 46)
  - Committee on Teaching meeting materials, 1960-1966 (Folder 47)
  - National Committee on Recruitment of College Teachers meeting agenda, 1957 (Folder 47)
  - Committee on Teaching in Colleges and Universities meeting minutes, 1960-1966 (Folder 47)
  - National Committee on General Education meeting materials, 1958-1960 (Folder 47)
  - Committee on Undergraduate Education meeting materials and administrative documents, 1965-1967 (Folder 48)
  - Executive Committee meeting, 1960 June (Folder 49)
  - Executive Committee meeting, brief minutes, 1972-1982 (Folder 50)
  - Election of officers, 1944-1969 (Folder 50)
- Conference materials, 1944-2005; 51-64 (Box 51-64)
  Includes program booklets, conference schedules, reports, workbooks, and video recordings
  - Tenure retreat, 1994 July (Folder 51)
  - Conference announcement pamphlets, 1996-2001 (Folder 51)
  - Report on post-tenure reviews (New Pathways II project), 2000 (Folder 51)
  - Tenure conference materials, 1996 (Folder 52)
  - Writings and articles on future of academic careers, 1978-1990 (Folder 52)
  - National Conference on Higher Education programs, 1969-1987 (Folder 53)
  - National Conference on Higher Education programs, 1988-2005 (Folder 54)
  - National Conference on Higher Education programs, 1997-2005 (Folder 55)
  - Assessment Forum programs, 1993-1998 (Folder 55)
  - Assessment Forum programs, 1999-2004 (Folder 56)
  - Conference on School/College Collaboration programs, 2001-2003 (Folder 56)
  - Forum on Faculty Roles and Rewards programs, 1993 (Folder 56)
  - Miscellaneous conference booklets and programs, 1980-2002 (Folder 57)
  - Higher Learning Commission Conference workbooks relating to assessing student learning, 1994-2004 (Folder 58)
  - Higher Learning Commission Conference workbooks relating to assessing student learning, 2003-2004 (Folder 59-60)
  - Strategic Directions conference, 2000-2002 (Folder 59-60)
  - National Conferences participants lists, 1946-1961 (Folder 61)
  - Constitutions and by-laws, 1980s (Folder 61)
  - Applications and correspondence with IRS attorneys over incorporation relationship with the National Education Association, 1969-1979 (Folder 61)
  - Programs, 1946-1961 (Folder 62)
  - National Conferences participants lists, 1962-1971 (Folder 62)
  - Video recordings of conferences, 2004-2005 (Folder 63-64)
    VHS videocassette tapes
    - "AAHE 2004 opening plenary Governor James Geringer keynote,", 2004 June 13 (Folder 63)
    - "AAHE 2004 opening plenary" (Folder 63)
    - "AAHE 2004 Tomas Rivera lecture" (Folder 63)
    - "AAHE 2004 Plenary-Higher education and government" (Folder 63)
    - "AAHE 2004 closing session Bernadine Chuck Fong,", 2004 June 15 (Folder 63)
    - "AAHE 2004 closing plenary" (Folder 63)
    - "AAHE 2004 plenary-Brown v. Topeka" (Folder 63)
    - "AAHE 2004 town hall meeting" (Folder 63)
    - "Clara Lovett interviews Claudio Sanchez,", 2004 March 25 (Folder 63)
      2 tapes
    - "2005 National Council on Higher Education (NCHE) Black Caucus, Event, Hotel Symonette, Derrick Bell" (Folder 64)
    - "2005 NCHE opening plenary, Rafael Rangel" (Folder 64)
    - "2005 NCHE Tomas Rivera lecture, Raul Yaguirre" (Folder 64)
    - "2005 NCHE closing plenary events" (Folder 64)
    - "2005 NCHE Public Perceptions of Higher Education: A Journalists' Roundtable" (Folder 64)
    - "AAHE 2004 plenary II, Ron Henry et al,", 2004 June 14 (Folder 64)
- Project file, 1971-2004; 65-125 (Box 65-125)
  Consists of correspondence, reports, studies, financial records, and memoranda
  - Membership, 1971-2001 (Folder 65-69)
    - Monthly activity reports, 1992 (Folder 65)
    - Monthly activity reports, 1987-1991 (Folder 65)
    - Statistics, 1991 February (Folder 65)
    - Board discussion, 1991 September (Folder 65:)
    - Analysis for executive committee meeting, 1989 May (Folder 65)
    - Analysis, 1988 (Folder 65)
    - Profile, 1987-1988 (Folder 65)
    - Survey, 1987 (Folder 65)
    - Issues, 1988-early 1990s (Folder 65)
    - Survey studies and budget, 1989-2000 (Folder 66)
    - "Welcome AAHE" banner, undated (Folder 67)
    - Monthly reports, 1982-1987 (Folder 67)
    - Budget, 2001 (Folder 67)
    - Member survey detail tables and appendix, 2001 (Folder 68)
    - Member survey detail tables, 2001 (Folder 69)
    - Writings and correspondence relating to faculty development and career change, 1980-1991 (Folder 69)
  - Forum on Faculty Roles and Rewards (FFRR), 1971-2002 (Folder 70-93)
    - Conference materials, 1998 (Folder 70: 1-2)
    - "An Inventory of Faculty Employment Policies,", 1996 March (Folder 70: 3)
    - List of executive board members, undated (Folder 70: 4)
    - Advisory panel, Atlanta, 1996 January (Folder 70: 5)
    - Advisory board meeting materials, 1996 March (Folder 70: 6)
    - New England Resource Center for Higher Education and AAHE regional conference materials, 1994-1995 (Folder 70: 7)
    - Fund for Improvement of Secondary Education (FIPSE) directors meeting, 1995-1997 (Folder 70: 8-10)
    - FIPSE project abstracts, 1994 October (Folder 70: 11)
    - FIPSE grant reports and proposals, 1992-1996 (Folder 71: 1-8)
    - FIPSE program book, 1995 (Folder 71: 9)
    - Start up notes, 1992 July (Folder 71: 10)
    - Reports, 2000 (Folder 71: 11-13)
    - FIPSE program book, 1996 (Folder 72)
    - Chicago advisory panel materials, 1997-1998 (Folder 72)
    - Grant award notification, 1998 August (Folder 73)
    - FFRR and FIPSE grant, 1999 (Folder 73)
    - Subject file, 1971-1995 (Folder 74-77)
      - Teaching, 1991-1992 (Folder 74: 1)
      - Teaching versus research, 1992-1993 (Folder 74: 2)
      - Teacher education, 1987-1993 (Folder 74: 3)
      - Interactive universities, 1991 (Folder 74: 4)
      - Service learning, 1992-1993 (Folder 74: 5)
      - Brooklyn College of the City University of New York, 1992 (Folder 74: 6)
      - University of Minnesota, 1992 (Folder 74: 7)
      - University of Virginia, 1990-1992 (Folder 74: 8)
      - San Jose State University, 1992 (Folder 74: 9)
      - Search results, 1992 (Folder 74: 10)
      - Faculty collective bargaining, 1992-1993 (Folder 74: 11)
      - Statistical data, 1993 (Folder 75: 1)
      - Tenure and racial/gender issues, 1971-1995 (Folder 75: 2-10)
      - Tenure in the context of higher education, 1993-1995 (Folder 75: 11-19)
      - External attacks on tenure, 1988-1993 (Folder 75: 20-22)
      - Post-tenure evaluation, 1986-1995 (Folder 75: 23-28)
      - Tenure in the context of higher education, 1993-1995 (Folder 75: 11-19)
      - Ripley's file, 1994-1995 (Folder 75: 29-31)
      - Tenure and professional schools, 1992 (Folder 75: 32)
      - Adjuncts and tenure, 1993-1995 (Folder 75: 33-38)
      - Bennington articles, 1995 (Folder 75: 39-41)
      - Alternatives to tenure, 1982-1994 (Folder 75: 42-47)
      - Campuses without tenure, 1995 (Folder 75: 48-49)
      - Professional service, 1992-1995 (Folder 75: 50)
      - Evaluating faculty work, 1990-1994 (Folder 76: 1)
      - Financing higher education, 1992-1994 (Folder 76: 2)
      - Faculty governance, 1990-1992 (Folder 76: 3)
      - Promotion and tenure, 1992 (Folder 76: 4)
      - New Pathways, undated (Folder 76: 5)
      - Tenure-personal and professional issues, 1993 (Folder 76: 6)
      - Airlie House, 1994 (Folder 76: 7)
      - Chronicle articles/issues, 1995 (Folder 77: 1)
      - Legal aspects of tenure, 1994 (Folder 77: 2)
      - AAHE publications, 1979-1994 (Folder 77: 3)
      - Tenure and mandatory retirement, 1991 (Folder 77: 4)
      - In defense of tenure, 1993 (Folder 77: 5)
      - Academe, 1995 (Folder 77: 6)
      - Contemporary universities, 1994 (Folder 77: 7)
      - Theory and practice, 1989 (Folder 77: 8)
      - Adult development, 1992 (Folder 77: 9)
    - Ernest L. Boyer (Carnegie Foundation) correspondence, 1992-1993 (Folder 78: 1-2)
    - Survey materials, probably 1992 (Folder 78: 3-4)
    - Proposals for 1993 conference, 1992 (Folder 78: 5)
    - Unpublished papers, 1992-1993 (Folder 78: 6)
    - Conference materials, 1993 (Folder 79)
    - Correspondence, bulletins, and mailings, 1992-1993 (Folder 80)
    - Correspondence, 1992-1993 (Folder 81)
    - Correspondence, 1993 January-July (Folder 82)
    - Airlie House retreat materials, 1992 (Folder 82)
    - Information requests, 1993 (Folder 82)
    - Granting foundations, 1993-1999 (Folder 83)
    - Granting foundations, 1998-2000 (Folder 84)
    - Granting foundations, 1994-2002 (Folder 85)
    - Granting foundations, 1996-2001 (Folder 86)
    - Research on faculty reward systems at public and private universities, 1991-1994 (Folder 86)
      Includes policies, correspondence, and writings regarding university faculty reward systems
    - Research on faculty reward systems at public and private universities, 1992-1993 (Folder 87-91)
    - Press releases and correspondence, 1992-1995 (Folder 92-93)
  - Urban University Portfolios Project, 1997-2001 (Folder 94-100)
    Includes public and private universities annual reports, progress reports, and research on grant funding
    - Urban University Portfolios Project files, 2000 (Folder 94)
    - Urban University Portfolios Project files, 1998-1999 (Folder 95)
    - Urban University Portfolios Project files, 1998-2000 (Folder 96)
      Includes conference and meeting materials
    - Urban University Portfolios Project files, 1998-2001 (Folder 97)
    - Urban University Portfolios Project files, 1999-2000 (Folder 98)
    - Urban University Portfolios Project files, 2000 (Folder 99)
    - Urban University Portfolios Project grants, 2001 (Folder 100)
  - New Pathways and New Pathways II, 1995-2000 (Folder 101-109)
    - Correspondence, proposals, and reports for universities, 1998-2000 (Folder 101)
    - New Pathways (NP), 1998 (Folder 102: 1)
    - NP II-IRC mailing, 1998 February (Folder 102: 2)
    - NP II session announcement, 1998 (Folder 102: 3)
    - Preliminary meeting information, 1998 (Folder 102: 4)
    - NP II meeting notes, 1998 May 29 (Folder 102: 5)
    - Pre-meeting at FFRR conference, 2000 (Folder 102: 6)
    - Tenure process meeting, 1998 October (Folder 102: 7)
    - Tenure process meeting logistics, 1998 October (Folder 102: 8)
    - Post-tenure review design protocol meeting logistics, 1998 November (Folder 102: 9)
    - Post-tenure review design protocol, 1998 November (Folder 102: 10)
    - Post-tenure review mini-grant colloquium materials, 1999 June-July (Folder 102: 11-14)
    - Minigrant colloquium and related materials, 1999 (Folder 103: 1-14)
    - Outcomes assessment and related materials, 1998 (Folder 103: 15-28)
    - Correspondence, proposals, and reports for universities, 1998-2000 (contd.) (Folder 104: 1-11)
    - Responses to project proposal, 1995 (Folder 104: 12-13)
    - Budget, 1998 (Folder 104: 14)
    - Reports and summaries, 1997 (Folder 104: 15-16)
    - Advisory panel, 1996 (Folder 104: 17)
    - Working papers, correspondence, and proposals, 1994-1996 (Folder 105)
    - Working papers, correspondence, and proposals, 1996 (Folder 106)
    - Working papers, 1996 (Folder 107: 1-7)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1998 (Folder 107: 8)
    - Press mentions, 1998 (Folder 107: 9)
    - Start up correspondence, 1998 (Folder 107: 10)
    - Start up plans, 1998 (Folder 107: 11)
    - Workshop, 1998 (Folder 107: 12)
    - Timelines, 1998 (Folder 107: 13)
    - Reports to project funders, 1998-1999 (Folder 107: 14-19)
    - Proposals and other project files, 1997-2000 (Folder 108)
    - New Pathways materials, 1995-1998 (Folder 109)
  - AAHE Teaching Initiative and teacher assessment practices notes, drafts, and correspondence, 1987-1991 (Folder 110)
  - Exxon Education Foundation correspondence and assessment forum materials, 1990 (Folder 110)
  - Teaching portfolios project, 1991-1994 (Folder 111-115)
    - Colleges and universities' response to questionnaire regarding portfolios and assessment, 1991-1992 (Folder 111)
    - Case studies and writings on teaching portfolios, 1991-1994 (Folder 112)
    - Case studies and writings on teaching portfolios, 1991-1994 (Folder 113)
    - Committee on Professional Recognition and Rewards site visit binder, 1993 (Folder 114: 1)
    - Sample portfolio entries and guidelines, 1992 (Folder 114: 2-17)
    - Teaching cases project workshop materials, 1992-1993 (Folder 115)
    - Teaching cases project conference materials, 1992-1993 (Folder 116)
  - Publications, 1980-2005 (Folder 117-120)
    - Change editorial board meeting materials, 1998-1995 (Folder 117)
    - Change publisher's materials, 1980-1987 (Folder 118)
    - Change correspondence and budget, 1988-2004 (Folder 119)
    - Change correspondence, budget, and advertisements, 1988-2004 (Folder 120)
      Includes materials relating to Heldref Publications
  - Other projects, 1986-2004, undated (Folder 121-125)
    - Department of Education meeting correspondence, 1987 (Folder 121: 1)
    - Total Quality Management project, 1990-1991 (Folder 121: 2-4)
    - Assessment workshop overhead transparencies, undated (Folder 121: 5-8)
    - Continuous Quality Improvement proposal from AAHE, 1992 December (Folder 121: 9)
    - Management Frontiers Pty Limited and Russell Edgerton correspondence, 1995 (Folder 121: 10)
    - Technology projects, 1994-1995 (Folder 121: 11-12)
    - Total Quality Management project, 1994-1996 (Folder 122)
    - Service learning projects, 1993-1995 (Folder 123)
    - Campus Compact, 1986-1995 (Folder 123)
    - Summer Academy, 2003-2004 (Folder 124)
    - Granting foundations correspondence, 1986-1989 (Folder 124)
    - Summer Academy, 1996-2001 (Folder 125)
- Subject file, 1978-2005; 126-129 (Box 126-129)
  Correspondence, memoranda, articles, studies, and clippings on different topics relating to education and academia and to the association's constituencies
  - Search committees, 1985-1990 (Folder 126)